<!DOCTYPE html>
<html lang="en">
<head>
  <meta charset="UTF-8">
  <meta http-equiv="X-UA-Compatible" content="IE=edge">
  <meta name="viewport" content="width=device-width, initial-scale=1.0">
  <title>2-45.pm • Ronan Limon Duparcmeur, fractional CTO and Renaissance developer for hire</title>
<meta name="description" content="I'm Ronan; I help companies build great apps and great teams.">
<meta name="author" content="Ronan Limon Duparcmeur">

<link rel="canonical" href="https://2-45.pm/blog/feed.xml" />







  <link rel="stylesheet" href="/css/2-45.css">
  
  
  <link rel="me" href="https://ruby.social/@r3trofitted">
  
  <script defer data-domain="2-45.pm" src="https://plausible.io/js/script.js"></script>
</head>
<body id="grainy-dinosaur">
  <header>
  <nav id="primary-nav">
    <ul class="inline-list">
      <li><a href="/">2-45.pm</a></li>
      <li><a href="/work-with-me.html">Work with me</a></li>
      <li><a href="/blog/">Blog</a></li>
      <li><a href="/articles/">Tech articles</a></li>
    </ul>
  </nav>
</header>
  <main>
    <article
  itemscope itemtype="http://schema.org/BlogPosting" 
  class="post h-entry "
  data-category="miscellanea"
  
  >
  <header class="post-header">
    <h2 class="post-title p-name" itemprop="name headline">
      Grainy Dinosaurs
    </h2>
    <p class="post-meta">
      <time class="dt-published" datetime="2023-11-19T20:04:43+01:00" itemprop="datePublished">
        Nov 19, 2023
      </time>
  </header>

  <div class="post-content e-content" itemprop="articleBody">
    <?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  

  <id>https://2-45.pm/blog/</id>
  <title>Grainy Dinosaurs</title>
  <updated>2023-12-06T09:30:34+01:00</updated>

  <author>
    <name>Ronan Limon Duparcmeur</name>
    <email>ronan@2-45.pm</email>
  </author>

  <link href="https://2-45.pm/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" />
  <link href="https://2-45.pm/blog" />

  <rights> © Ronan Limon Duparcmeur - ronan@2-45.pm </rights>
  
  
    <entry>
      <id>https://2-45.pm/blog/blog/2023/12/06/i-wasn-t-meant-to-be-a-rock-star.html</id>
      <title>I wasn&#39;t meant to be a /rock ?star/</title>
      <updated>2023-12-06T09:30:34+01:00</updated>

      <link rel="alternate" href="https://2-45.pm/blog/blog/2023/12/06/i-wasn-t-meant-to-be-a-rock-star.html" />

      <published>2023-12-06T09:30:34+01:00</published>
      <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Even since I heard about it, I&amp;rsquo;ve been fond of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://codewithrockstar.com&quot;&gt;Rockstar&lt;/a&gt; programming language. 
Or, more precisely, I&amp;rsquo;ve been fond of the humor behind this langage, and the fact Rockstar it is basically a 
joke &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4xgx4k83zzc&quot;&gt;pushed to eleven&lt;/a&gt;, with actual implementations and potentially 
actual programs to be written.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I tried to do the Advent of Code using Rockstar, but immediately hit a roadblock. This year, I decided 
to push through and accidentally committed to do so by &lt;a href=&quot;https://ruby.social/@r3trofitted/111427212436421499&quot;&gt;@ing by Jeff Atwood&lt;/a&gt;. 
Unfortunately, this proved to be a commitment I could not hold to, and I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to quit after solving the first challenge (which took me several 
days to do). However, this was a learning experience; let me share it with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;down&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://music.apple.com/fr/album/down/1045519155&quot;&gt;Down&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a long-time Ruby developer, I easily forget how good I have things. Ruby is a high-level language optimized 
for developer happiness, after all. Rockstar is certainly Turing-complete, but is very bare-bones. No objects. 
No regular expressions. No iterators. No data structure but arrays. If you want anymore more than loops and 
variables, you&amp;rsquo;ll have to build it yourself. In a way, it felt like 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://2-45.pm/articles/z80asm/2023/08/31/jurassic-stack.html&quot;&gt;programming in Assembly&lt;/a&gt;, or playing survival 
Minecraft. You want an enchanting table? Start punching trees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, like with Minecraft, this is part of the game, but I wasn&amp;rsquo;t prepared for the time it takes to do 
anything. I eventually started writing a library of functions, and in retrospect I should have done that 
from the start. Go over my strategy, identify the tools I&amp;rsquo;ll need, and create them. Instead, I spent 
too much time stumbling my way procedurally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cryptic-writings&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://music.apple.com/fr/album/countdown-to-extinction-live/703019036&quot;&gt;Cryptic Writings&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What makes Rockstar great are the &lt;a href=&quot;https://codewithrockstar.com/docs#:~:text=undefined&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;poetic literals&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;-,Poetic%20Literals,-Rockstar%20also): 
ways to assign constants, strings or integers to variables using plain English. &lt;code&gt;My love is true&lt;/code&gt; assigns 
the constant &lt;code&gt;true&lt;/code&gt; to the variable &lt;code&gt;my love&lt;/code&gt;; 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://music.apple.com/fr/album/made-the-same/1116637128?i=1116637291&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Your mind is thinking madness&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
 assign the value &lt;code&gt;87&lt;/code&gt; to the variable &lt;code&gt;your mind&lt;/code&gt;; 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://music.apple.com/fr/album/seventeen/1092723303?i=1092723307&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Daddy says she&#39;s too young but she&#39;s old enough for me&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; 
assigns the value &lt;code&gt;she&#39;s too young but she&#39;s old enough for me&lt;/code&gt; to the variable &lt;code&gt;Daddy&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is clever and fun, and I was expecting to spend most of my time searching for thematic literals, instead 
of finding my way through my own code. I failed to anticipate how quickly code can be obfuscated. This is 
especially true when you need to assign values like 0 or 1, for which you need to use 10- and 11-letter words – 
at a glance, it&amp;rsquo;s hard to tell how many letters a long word has.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compounding this is the fact that poetic literals can only be used in variable assignments. So if you 
need a scalar value in an operation – say, to evaluate the exit condition of a loop – you need to first 
go through a variable, and then use it in the operation. All this boilerplate takes a lot of headspace very fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again, this is completely fair given the purpose of Rockstar, but it makes for a harder challenge 
than I was expecting. I eventually came up with techniques to make the code easier to decrypt, such as using 
words starting in i, j or k for loop counters (&lt;code&gt;The idol is disharmony&lt;/code&gt; for &lt;code&gt;i = 0&lt;/code&gt;), or pre-assigning 
“constants” for recurring values like 0. But even then, reading my Rockstar was really hard. Forget 
“yourself in 6 months”, I had to care about myself in 6 minutes! In the end, I had to comment every line with 
pseudo-code, which is not very rock&amp;rsquo;n roll.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;achtung-baby&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://music.apple.com/fr/album/achtung-baby/1443063058&quot;&gt;Achtung Baby&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adding these comments led me to a bug in Rockstar, or at least in Sinatra&amp;rsquo;s implementation (when 
assigning a literal string, comments put at the end of the line are considered part of the string). 
But, in truth, this was only one among many, though some are certainly more unfortunate consequences of 
the language&amp;rsquo;s design that actual implementation issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, you cannot re-assign a new, empty array to a variable. Because the same keyword, &lt;code&gt;rock&lt;/code&gt;, 
is used to create a new array or wrap an exiting variable into a new array, using it several times 
with the same variable name – in a loop, for example – only re-uses the array created the first time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the same token, you can only get the length of an array by &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/RockstarLang/rockstar/issues/300&quot;&gt;evaluating it in a scalar context&lt;/a&gt; – 
like adding 0 to it. This probably counts more as boilerplate than a defect, but still, I tripped 
more than once on this peculiarity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, because Rockstar wasn&amp;rsquo;t meant to be taken seriously, it is difficult to find a serious 
interpreter for it. I eventually used &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/RockstarLang/rockstar/tree/main/satriani&quot;&gt;Satriani&lt;/a&gt;, 
a JS implementation that is also the reference for the language, but because of 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/RockstarLang/rockstar/issues/297&quot;&gt;unsolved issues with piped input&lt;/a&gt;, I only did so 
after trying the Ruby implementation, and the Rust one – and none of them worked properly. I would be 
unkind to list the bugs I encountered with any of these 3 implementations or complain about them, but if 
you want to try out Rockstar, be prepared: its edges are still very rough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;good-humor-saint-etienne&quot;&gt;Good Humor (Saint Etienne)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, it took me 3 days to finish the first challenge. Granted, it was over a week-end, and I didn&amp;rsquo;t 
spend my whole days on it, but still – we&amp;rsquo;re talking orders of magnitude what would have taken me in Ruby, 
for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trying to write a simple program in an unreliable, confusing and low-level language really made me 
feel like some very new developers I encountered in my career: quickly disoriented in the codebase, losing 
track of their initial intent, and resorting to trying out anything in the hope that it works, without 
understanding why. This is inefficient and unpleasant. It refilled my empathy for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, even if I&amp;rsquo;m not entirely happy with my final result, I&amp;rsquo;m glad to see that I did not give up when put 
in this uncomfortable position. In fact, I could not let it go – like a Wordle from Hell, solving this 
challenge in Rockstar became a personal brain-teaser that I eventually overcame. Even if it drained all 
my desire to continue with the Advent of Code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who knows, maybe I&amp;rsquo;ll try again next year? But this time, I&amp;rsquo;ll be even more prepared, with a library of 
basic functions, and solid habits to keep track of the &lt;em&gt;logic&lt;/em&gt; in the program before going over it and 
thinking about the lexical fields, and the different synonyms available for sex, drugs, and party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, if you want to read my poetry, I&amp;rsquo;ve &lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/r3trofitted/24086d4bd9263ddee1679b5443c89f91&quot;&gt;put it in a gist&lt;/a&gt;, 
and here is the uncommented version:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Mister Presents takes your wish, your sins and your prayers
Let the ice be your prayers
The judge is hypnotized
Shatter your wish
The heart is liveliness
Let the love be lies
Let the gift be your sins at the ice
Let the coal be your wish at the judge
Until the gift is nothing
Let the coal be your wish at the judge
If the gift is the coal
Let the love be true
Build the ice up
Build the judge up
Let the gift be your sins at the ice
If the love is true and the judge is as high as the heart with your wish
Let the truth be the ice without the judge
Give it back

Take it to the top

If the gift is your wish at the heart
The judge is perseverant
Build the ice up
Let the gift be your sins at the ice
Take it to the top

Let the love be lies
The judge is deflowered
Build the ice up
Let the gift be your sins at the ice




The Arbiter takes the sound
While the sound ain&#39;t nothing
Roll the sound into the vibe
If the vibe ain&#39;t mysterious
Rock the vibe into the wave


The crest is amplitudes
The rush is bewildering
Let the glory be the wave at the crest
Let the end be the wave without the rush
Let the pride be the wave at the end
Rock the glory
Rock the glory with the pride
Unite the glory into the dream
Burn the dream
Give it back




The beat says YELL!
Listen to the pulse
Shatter the pulse into your soul with the beat

The revelation is earthlight
The start is crucifixion
Your lover is joyfulness
The fear is subjugation
Let the dance be your lover without the fear
Rock you like &quot;one&quot;
Rock you like &quot;two&quot;
Rock you like &quot;three&quot;
Rock you like &quot;four&quot;
Rock you like &quot;five&quot;
Rock you like &quot;six&quot;
Rock you like &quot;seven&quot;
Rock you like &quot;eight&quot;
Rock you like &quot;nine&quot;
While your soul ain&#39;t gone
The sound is lies
Rock the sound
Roll your soul into my words
My sign is resilience
Your name is consequence
The idol is flamboyant
The herald is disharmony
Until the idol is my sign with you
Let the joker be your name with the idol
Let the drug be Mister Presents taking the joker, my words &#39;n&#39; the herald
If the drug is as high as your lover
Let the sound at the drug be the joker
Let the herald be your name with the drug
Take it to the top

Let the herald be my sign
Build the idol up

The idol is disharmony
The herald is flamboyant
Until the idol is my sign with you
Let the joker be your name with the idol
Let the killer be you at the idol
Let the drug be Mister Presents taking the killer, my words &#39;n&#39; the herald
If the drug is as high as your lover
Let the sound at the drug be the joker
Let the herald be your name with the drug
Take it to the top

Let the herald be my sign
Build the idol up

Let the faith be the Arbiter taking the sound
Let the revelation be the revelation with the faith

Shout the revelation
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <id>https://2-45.pm/blog/blog/a-dash-of-milk/2023/11/14/issue-8.html</id>
      <title>A dash of milk #8</title>
      <updated>2023-11-24T11:27:00+01:00</updated>

      <link rel="alternate" href="https://2-45.pm/blog/blog/a-dash-of-milk/2023/11/14/issue-8.html" />

      <published>2023-11-24T11:27:00+01:00</published>
      <content type="html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;http-303-redirects-with-anchor-not-respected&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/hotwired/turbo/issues/211&quot;&gt;HTTP 303 Redirects with anchor not respected&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An unexpected issue with Turbo that I came across while working on a pet project. It&amp;rsquo;s all the more 
a bummer that the problem is not really with Turbo, but &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/whatwg/fetch/issues/1167&quot;&gt;with &lt;code&gt;fetch()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. 
The silver lining is that I learned a couple of things through this, starting with the fact that there is 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://fetch.spec.whatwg.org&quot;&gt;a whole spec for fetching&lt;/a&gt; (which goes beyond the JS function).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;spicy-web&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.spicyweb.dev&quot;&gt;Spicy Web&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I may be late to the party here, since Jared White is a name that sounds familiar, but Spicy Web is yet 
another heartwarming example of the Revenge of the Simple Web. I sense a backlash brewing against the over-engineering 
of the web in the last decade, and every single week I stumble on another brilliant piece of advocacy for a return 
to HTML and CSS by the book – which are very powerful now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;wait-is-cloud-bad&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://newsletter.goodtechthings.com/p/wait-is-cloud-bad&quot;&gt;Wait, is cloud bad?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An interesting counter-take on DHH&amp;rsquo;s recent advocacy for exiting the cloud. I don&amp;rsquo;t necessarily agree with the author 
on everything, but I liked his tone. Being myself (moderately) excited at the prospect of being able to do go back to the 
good old days, including when it comes to sysadmin stuff, I appreciate a different perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;posse&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://indieweb.org/POSSE&quot;&gt;POSSE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talking about the good old days, &lt;a href=&quot;https://justin.searls.co/takes/2023-10-30-13h57m54s/&quot;&gt;a toot by Justin Searls&lt;/a&gt; pointed 
me towards this nice branding of a cool concept. I already have too many projects in progress, but redoing this 
site to making it POSSE-compliant is now on top of the TODO pile. The 90&amp;rsquo;s are back, I&amp;rsquo;m telling you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;geist&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://vercel.com/font/mono&quot;&gt;Geist&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As &lt;a href=&quot;https://2-45.pm/2023/06/26/no-milk-no-sugar-4.html&quot;&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve written already&lt;/a&gt;, I&amp;rsquo;m a sucker for fonts. This one looked 
nice, and its website really sells it well. But, for some reason, I didn&amp;rsquo;t like it in practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;monaspace&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://monaspace.githubnext.com&quot;&gt;Monaspace&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;… And yet, I am going all-in on the Monaspace family – more precisely, on Monaspace Neon, semi-wide and ultra-light. 
Probably because it looks a bit like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linotype.com/342843/eurostile-family.html&quot;&gt;Eurostile&lt;/a&gt;, my favorite fonts 
of all time, as overused as it may be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(So far, the transition to Monaspace Neon from my dead Monofur is going rather well, even it is less pleasing when writing 
prose.)&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <id>https://2-45.pm/blog/blog/2023/11/05/humility-check.html</id>
      <title>Humility check</title>
      <updated>2023-11-05T21:12:00+01:00</updated>

      <link rel="alternate" href="https://2-45.pm/blog/blog/2023/11/05/humility-check.html" />

      <published>2023-11-05T21:12:00+01:00</published>
      <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I consider myself a solid developer, especially with Ruby and Rails. After all, I&amp;rsquo;ve been writing code and 
building systems for more than twenty years now. However, I&amp;rsquo;m weary of becoming complacent, or even worse, 
overestimating abilities that would be declining without me realizing it. That is why I keep practicing and 
always welcome a challenge or an assessment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And such a test is exactly what I took a couple of days ago, partially to find new consulting opportunities, 
but mostly to see how I measured. Well, let&amp;rsquo;s just say that it was a learning, and humbling, experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-test&quot;&gt;The test&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frankly, it was a good test. Technical tests are not that easy to write. They must be realistic, and yet not require 
knowledge of a specific business domain. They should cover high- and low-level stuff, and yet be focused. They should 
look like actual application code, and yet keep the boilerplate to a minimum. It&amp;rsquo;s a tricky balance, and I found this 
test well-balanced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sign of the times, the test&amp;rsquo;s setup was “Rails as a back-end for a REST API”. So, very realistic, but also a bit 
sad, since it&amp;rsquo;s basically misusing my favorite framework. Still, the use case was very clear, coherent, and well laid 
out. The test came with a skeleton app and some integration specs; the goal was mostly to fill in the blanks in the code 
to make the specs pass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would love to complain about the non-RESTful nature of the app&amp;rsquo;s resources, its choice of RSpec over Minitest, or 
the insistence on using some kind of service layer, and blame my poor performance on these, but that would be dishonest. 
For better or worse, this structure is extremely common in 2023, and as I&amp;rsquo;ve said, good tests are realistic.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-performance&quot;&gt;My performance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I failed miserably. Or rather: I eventually came up with a solution that I find pretty good, but it took me way longer 
than the allocated time. So what did I do wrong?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, what I did &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; do wrong: I didn&amp;rsquo;t waste time setting up my environment, and I didn&amp;rsquo;t waste time 
looking stuff up online, basically filling in holes in my knowledge with Stack Overflow snippets. I mention these things 
because they are among the obvious red flags that I look for when I am the one doing the evaluation. At least my basics 
were covered. So what took me so long?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, I &lt;strong&gt;didn&amp;rsquo;t study the code enough before diving in&lt;/strong&gt;. Now that I think about it, this is the kind of 
common advice that I was given when I was a student – or that I could give my son now. Don&amp;rsquo;t rush, and read carefully 
the wording of the problem. And the code you start with is part of this wording! But because I didn&amp;rsquo;t do that, I 
stumbled upon stupid things that broke my flow – things like not looking at the &lt;code&gt;schema.rb&lt;/code&gt; file to see that a given 
attribute that is passed as a string is actually stored as an integer, and therefore the model should declare an &lt;code&gt;enum&lt;/code&gt;. 
To be honest, I cursed every time I lost 20 seconds on what felt like unfair traps, but in retrospect, these are part of 
the game, and something you should always do in real life anyway. So, this recurring loss of footing is on me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, I couldn&amp;rsquo;t help myself &lt;strong&gt;coding with my ego&lt;/strong&gt;, and obsessing too much and too early on &lt;em&gt;making it right&lt;/em&gt;, 
instead of ensuring that I had &lt;em&gt;made it work&lt;/em&gt; everywhere first. It&amp;rsquo;s a weakness I know well, now, and yet once again 
it was stronger than me. This was especially true on the algorithmic part of the test. I&amp;rsquo;m not very good when it comes to 
core CS stuff, and I felt an extra impulse to &lt;strong&gt;show off&lt;/strong&gt; and try to do something clever, which took me a very 
long time to come up with, instead of brute-forcing my way through the problem. Now, in my defense, one of my motivations 
for taking this test was to have fun and try new things, and I had never had a good reason to use &lt;code&gt;Array#slice_when&lt;/code&gt; 
before. I did have fun, and I did learn new things, but it was unwise and it is the main reason why I lost so much time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, in truth, I could still have pulled it off in time if I had been more familiar with the expected architecture. 
The app was technically using Rails, but not following the Rails Ways™, and the seemingly incoherent requirements that 
ensued from this architecture &lt;strong&gt;got me confused&lt;/strong&gt;. It became a puzzle I could not figure out – I got the objects 
that the solution wanted, and the responsibilities they had to have, but couldn&amp;rsquo;t find a way to dispatch the latter 
among the former as the test wanted me to. Or not in a way that made sense to me, anyway. I eventually came up with 
something that worked, but it didn&amp;rsquo;t feel &lt;em&gt;right&lt;/em&gt;. And yet, coming up with it took me a very long time – in fact, I 
had to start again from scratch, doing things “my way”, and then backtracking to something that would satisfy the 
requirements of the test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-was-revealed&quot;&gt;What was revealed?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This mismatch between what I think was expected of the candidates, and the way I usually build a Rails app, gives 
me pause. I certainly don&amp;rsquo;t want to put my failing on the test itself or look for excuses. I made mistakes because 
of my own shortcomings, there&amp;rsquo;s no denying that. And yet, if indeed I reversed-engineered properly the test (which is 
a big &lt;em&gt;if&lt;/em&gt;), I wonder if I should make a big deal out of this poor performance. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t come up with a solution 
that I would advise against anyway, in a classic case of misusing a framework that I (supposedly) know how to use well. 
Should I stick to my guns, ignore these perversions, and feel fine about my own lack of awareness, or should I step 
down from my pedestal, go with the flow, and become familiar with these misguided but common approaches to “a Rails 
backend”?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Still, the more I thought about this test, the more issues I had with it, as an example of poor practices. I&amp;rsquo;ll 
  certainly come back to this in future posts.&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <id>https://2-45.pm/blog/blog/2023/10/31/the-fall-of-the-house-of-usher.html</id>
      <title>The Fall of the House of Usher</title>
      <updated>2023-10-31T11:59:00+01:00</updated>

      <link rel="alternate" href="https://2-45.pm/blog/blog/2023/10/31/the-fall-of-the-house-of-usher.html" />

      <published>2023-10-31T11:59:00+01:00</published>
      <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I really, really liked &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imdb.com/title/tt10574558/&quot;&gt;Midnight Mass&lt;/a&gt;. So much so that it got me to 
catch up with Mike Flanagan&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Haunting of&amp;rdquo; shows, which were, say, of uneven quality but still enjoyable. And 
it got me rather excited for The Fall of the House of Usher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that I&amp;rsquo;ve watched this latest show, the more I think about it, the more I see issues in its pacing, tone, text and 
subtext, to the point that I honestly cannot be bothered to write a full post about it. Every pertinent opinion 
I could give can be found in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://slate.com/culture/2023/10/the-fall-of-the-house-of-usher-netflix-mike-flanagan-edgar-allan-poe-adaptation.html&quot;&gt;Slate review&lt;/a&gt; that 
I carefully refrained from reading before watching the show. Or, for a more personal touch, in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ruby.social/@r3trofitted/111319120972931721&quot;&gt;three&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://ruby.social/@r3trofitted/111323798762943647&quot;&gt;toots&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://ruby.social/@r3trofitted/111324521630572845&quot;&gt;I posted&lt;/a&gt; 
during my quasi-binging:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I like Mike Flanagan’s work, and I LOVED Midnight Mass, but I’m pretty disappointed by The Fall of the House of Usher 
so far (meaning after 2 episodes).&lt;br /&gt;
↳ Mark Hamill is pretty cool, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Almost done with the Fall of the House of Usher. Watching the Flanacast again is nice, but this series really suffers 
from Netflixis: it had good material for a movie but it got diluted to make too many episodes, and then padded with 
over-styling. And the references to Poe’s works and current events are as artificial as the sets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Final thoughts on The Fall of the House of Usher: the poetry is really good (no shit, Sherlock) but the social 
commentary is hollow (even if well-intended).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <id>https://2-45.pm/blog/blog/a-dash-of-milk/2023/10/30/issue-7.html</id>
      <title>A dash of milk #7</title>
      <updated>2023-10-24T09:03:00+02:00</updated>

      <link rel="alternate" href="https://2-45.pm/blog/blog/a-dash-of-milk/2023/10/30/issue-7.html" />

      <published>2023-10-24T09:03:00+02:00</published>
      <content type="html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;its-2023-here-is-why-your-web-design-sucks&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://heather-buchel.com/blog/2023/10/why-your-web-design-sucks/&quot;&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s 2023, here is why your web design sucks.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably the best article I&amp;rsquo;ve stumbled upon in the past couple of weeks. Reading it go me so excited that I 
couldn&amp;rsquo;t help but forwarding it around, especially to designers or managers I&amp;rsquo;ve worked with in the past. Heather 
Buchel explains exactly what I&amp;rsquo;ve been trying to say for years, but way better than I ever could, and with 
an extra dash of insights (especially regarding gender-based territoriality). And I love her tone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;whitespace-characters-to-copy-and-paste&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://qwerty.dev/whitespace/&quot;&gt;Whitespace Characters to Copy and Paste&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, more importantly, whitespace characters to learn about. I&amp;rsquo;m a rather lenient person, but when it comes to 
typography, I gladly nitpick like the nerd I am (deep inside). I stumbled upon this great site when searching 
for a design solution to a &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;spacing issue&lt;/a&gt; in my latest pet project. You can bet that it&amp;rsquo;s now in my bookmarks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;yaml-multiline&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://yaml-multiline.info&quot;&gt;YAML Multiline&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another reference I&amp;rsquo;m happy to bookmark, now that I&amp;rsquo;m back to 1998 and actually browser features like bookmarks 
again. (By the way, do you remember &lt;a href=&quot;https://pinboard.in/u:r3trofitted/&quot;&gt;Pinboard&lt;/a&gt;?) Anyway, YAML is confusing 
and will occasionally trip you up, hopefully this will help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;super-color-palette&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://supercolorpalette.com&quot;&gt;Super Color Palette&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another great tool, that I learned about through &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/@BJGpixel&quot;&gt;Brandon James Greers&lt;/a&gt; (who 
makes pictures out of tiny squares). I&amp;rsquo;ve been building up several new things recently, and UI design can be 
alien enough to stop me in my tracks, but this kind of tool helps a lot to push through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;constructing-subclasses-of-data-with-positional-arguments&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bugs.ruby-lang.org/issues/19278&quot;&gt;Constructing subclasses of Data with positional arguments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My original notes for the link where: &lt;em&gt;What a thread. Talk about tone.&lt;/em&gt; In hindsight, they suffice.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <id>https://2-45.pm/blog/blog/a-dash-of-milk/2023/10/23/issue-6.html</id>
      <title>A dash of milk #6</title>
      <updated>2023-10-23T09:38:00+02:00</updated>

      <link rel="alternate" href="https://2-45.pm/blog/blog/a-dash-of-milk/2023/10/23/issue-6.html" />

      <published>2023-10-23T09:38:00+02:00</published>
      <content type="html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;elmore-the-finest-one-of-all&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/mfNoPYChIqk&quot;&gt;Elmore: The Finest One of All&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve never been too fond of D&amp;amp;D, and especially not the 2nd edition, but a single illustration stuck me when 
I first saw it, in the Player&amp;rsquo;s Handbook that I borrowed from a classmate back in high school. It&amp;rsquo;s been more 
than 30 years now, and I still find this piece incredibly evocative. Well, obviously I&amp;rsquo;m not the only one, since 
this colorful YouTuber has managed to make a 30-minute video on it, and keep it interesting, too!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-little-told-story-about-the-bart-seat-slashing-gang-&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sfgate.com/bayarea/article/bart-seat-slasher-hurwitz-service-systems-inc-14544785.php&quot;&gt;The little-told story about the BART seat-slashing gang […]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I loved this story of unscrupulous people gaming a system they&amp;rsquo;re part of. I might reuse it in a Cyberpunk RED 
scenario, or cite it as an example of wrong incentives when giving management advice. Or both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-im-in-the-tailwind-cult&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://phoenixonrails.com/blog/why-im-in-the-tailwind-cult&quot;&gt;Why I&amp;rsquo;m in the Tailwind cult&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m still trying to understand the appeal of Tailwind. Unfortunately, this article didn&amp;rsquo;t convince me; it only 
reinforced my conviction that there are many web developers won&amp;rsquo;t don&amp;rsquo;t really care for the technical foundations, 
limitations and superpowers of the Web, and would prefer it to be more like a desktop environment. Which was already 
the case back in the days of ASP.NET 1.0. I&amp;rsquo;m not one of those people, but I still wonder if I&amp;rsquo;m missing out on 
something. I guess I have no choice but to try it out myself…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;writing-object-shape-friendly-code-in-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://island94.org/2023/10/writing-object-shape-friendly-code-in-ruby&quot;&gt;Writing Object Shape friendly code in Ruby&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is very interesting. At the same time, it is so counter-intuitive that I don&amp;rsquo;t ever see myself using it. And yet, 
I find it really cool, and I&amp;rsquo;m glad that this kind of optimization exists, as costly as it may be, for the people 
who need it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;that-useless-ruby-syntax-sugar-that-emerged-in-new-versions&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://zverok.space/blog/2023-10-02-syntax-sugar.html&quot;&gt;That useless Ruby syntax sugar that emerged in new versions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am definitely in the camp of the back-pushing people who don&amp;rsquo;t like, or at best don&amp;rsquo;t care for, the newest additions 
to Ruby – things like the numbers block parameters or the pattern matching. This is why I appreciate this series 
of articles, which could challenge my scepticism. (Like with the Tailwind article above, so far it hasn&amp;rsquo;t really 
worked, but that&amp;rsquo;s not important.)&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <id>https://2-45.pm/blog/blog/2023/10/02/euruko-2023.html</id>
      <title>Euruko 2023</title>
      <updated>2023-10-02T15:39:00+02:00</updated>

      <link rel="alternate" href="https://2-45.pm/blog/blog/2023/10/02/euruko-2023.html" />

      <published>2023-10-02T15:39:00+02:00</published>
      <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;After a pandemic lockdown and two stints in companies oblivious to the benefits of tech conferences (no wonder I didn&amp;rsquo;t 
stay), 2023 is the year where I&amp;rsquo;m finally attending confs again. I&amp;rsquo;ll be at Rails World in a few days, but last week, 
it was &lt;a href=&quot;https://2023.euruko.org&quot;&gt;Euruko&lt;/a&gt;. TL;DR: in spite of a few organisational hiccups, it was great and I had a blast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;venue-and-organisation&quot;&gt;Venue and organisation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being a bit of a homebody, and even more a complete ignorant of geography, I had a slight hesitation upon seeing that 
this year&amp;rsquo;s Euruko would be in Lithuania. It&amp;rsquo;s on the opposite side of Europe! But, bless be the EU, getting there was 
as easy as going to, say, &lt;a href=&quot;https://rubyonrails.org/world&quot;&gt;Amsterdam&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was expecting Vilnius to be charming, with some discrete relics of its Soviet past, and this exactly how it was. It is 
modern and yet history-rich, and very lively – I wasn&amp;rsquo;t expecting that many people on terrasses and paved streets. I went 
for a run one evening, through the old town with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7fDvxlK2FMc&quot;&gt;Carpenter Brut&lt;/a&gt; playing in 
my Airpods, and between the Renaissance façades&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, the occasional brutalist artefacts, the busy crowd and the soft public 
lighting, I felt like in the Prague hub of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eidosmontreal.com/games/deus-ex-mankind-divided/&quot;&gt;Deux Ex: Mankind Divided&lt;/a&gt;. 
Which was great (it is a good game after all).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conference took place in the main campus of VILNIUS TECH, a few minutes by car from the city center. I was initially 
disappointed to see that the venue was not practically accessible by foot, but it turned out not to be an issue: the 
organisers had put a perfectly fine transfer system and the ride was an extra opportunity for sightseeing. And the campus 
was ideal for a conference: modern, well-equipped, with plenty of room to sit or chat. The catering was, let&amp;rsquo;s say, 
canteen-level, which made sense in an university, I guess. Still, I don&amp;rsquo;t want to complain: these things are hard 
to organise, and we didn&amp;rsquo;t come for a gastronomical experience anyway. So, overall: the venue was fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, &lt;em&gt;fine&lt;/em&gt; could describe the whole of the organisation. Nothing was particularly astonishing, and since 2023 
was Ruby&amp;rsquo;s 30th anniversary, Euruko&amp;rsquo;s 20th, and Vilnius 700th, and was kind of expecting something really special, but 
this excessive hype is on me. There were a few unfortunate technical issues, but these things happen, and once again: 
organising a conference is a lot of difficult work, so having almost everything run smoothly is already a great 
success. My only serious complain is on the agenda – but I&amp;rsquo;ll come back to this later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-conference-talks&quot;&gt;The conference talks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m happy to say that the planned talks were exactly what I wanted from Euruko: varied&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, sometimes technical and 
sometimes aspirational, sometimes straightforward and sometimes weird, sometimes beginner-friendly and sometimes more 
advanced. My personal highlights are &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/srbaker&quot;&gt;Steven Baker&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s “Reflections on a Reluctant Revolution”, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/hasumikin&quot;&gt;Hitoshi Hasumi&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;A Beginner&amp;rsquo;s Complete Guide to Microcontroller Programming in Ruby&amp;rdquo; 
and, unsurprisingly, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/yukihiro_matz&quot;&gt;Matz&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s keynote on a sensitive topic: the GVL.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few talks stood out as not being especially Ruby-centric, such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/carlastabile&quot;&gt;Carla Urrea Stabile&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s 
(on passkeys), &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/chacon&quot;&gt;Scott Chacon&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s (on version control), or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/hana-harencarova&quot;&gt;Hana Harencarova&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s 
(on feature flags). Those did smell like sponsor talks, but each time the speakers were really nice and entertaining, 
and didn&amp;rsquo;t push for their respective companies&amp;rsquo; products. (And Carla, in particular, was very patient with the technical 
difficulties she had to endure.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-unconference-talks&quot;&gt;The unconference talks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the problematic ones. This year, Euruko&amp;rsquo;s organisers choose to dedicate half the agenda to ”unconference” talks 
– talks pitched and then given by audience members, without oversight by the selection committee. I&amp;rsquo;m fine with opening 
the stage to mere audience members, but 8 talks – that&amp;rsquo;s a bit much, to me at least, and it felt like padding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To their credit, all the speakers where confortable with the exercice and knew their material; however, most of the topics 
were not really interesting (IMHO once again; YMMV). Lots of talks about performance, for example, which is rarely a 
concern of mine. Still, I really enjoyed 2 of these unconference talks: Chikahiro Tokoro&amp;rsquo;s, because of the pure joy of 
programming that he radiated, and Johnny Shields&amp;rsquo;s, which was genuinely interesting from a technical point of view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-people-and-the-hallway-track&quot;&gt;The people and the hallway track&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though you definitely &lt;a href=&quot;https://hynek.me/articles/hallway-track/&quot;&gt;shouldn&amp;rsquo;t focus on it&lt;/a&gt;, the “hallway track”, and 
more generally the socialising, is the big appeal of conferences. And this is what made Euruko such a great experience 
for me this year. Going by myself instead of with a bunch of colleagues definitely helped, since I &lt;em&gt;had&lt;/em&gt; to mingle and 
join conversations. Socialising at conferences is a bit like TDD: it may seem like an extra burden at first, but once 
you do it, it becomes obvious that it&amp;rsquo;s the most important thing you could do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is something special in spending time talking about what is both a common passion and a daily, professional concern 
with people from a different-but-alike background. From a practical, pragmatic perspective, it is very enlightening – 
you get to compare experiences, challenge opinions and have yours challenged, and in the end learn a lot. It is stepping 
outside of one&amp;rsquo;s habits zone while being guaranteed to stay within one&amp;rsquo;s domain of expertise. A invaluable bowl of fresh 
air.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, more importantly, it recharges your passion batteries. I don&amp;rsquo;t envy, and don&amp;rsquo;t value a lot, developers who claim 
not to care about the language or framework they use. ”It&amp;rsquo;s just a tool&amp;rdquo; is misguided at best, and symptomatic at worst. 
I&amp;rsquo;m a firm believer in being passionate about one&amp;rsquo;s work – it is a luxury not everyone can afford, but because it is 
affordable in programming, we should all strive for it. And passion is also fuelled by the feeling of belonging to a 
community, to be among peers, and by sharing time and ideas with them. This is especially true in Ruby, the 
friendliest and smartest language, with the friendliest and smartest community (MINASWAN FTW). The time I spent talking 
with fellow rubyists of all walks of life was the most rewarding of the whole 3 days. It taught me a lot, energised me 
a lot, and renewed my love for my work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;takeaways&quot;&gt;Takeaways&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But besides a full charge, did I bring back any souvenirs from my trip to Vilnius? Yes, a couple, in fact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, Ruby is &lt;em&gt;old&lt;/em&gt;. It is common to say that is it &lt;em&gt;mature&lt;/em&gt;, but this is an euphemism. Ruby has a long history, 
and is showed throughout the conference – in Stephen Backer&amp;rsquo;s memories of the early days of the Agile Manifesto and 
the famous names of this era, in Matz&amp;rsquo;s rationals for the GVL (a design choice made at a time when computers had only 
one core), and in the number of participants with 15, 20 or 25 years of experience with Ruby. Ruby&amp;rsquo;s popularity came 
late, but it doesn&amp;rsquo;t negate the fact that Ruby&amp;rsquo;s history is long, and covers several generations of developers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yet, Ruby ages gracefully. That is in part due, in think, to the core team&amp;rsquo;s excellent leadership, and ability to 
accept change and new features, while having the courage to refuse proposals that wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be right. Once again, Matz&amp;rsquo;s 
thoughts on the GVL embody this brave balance: just because nowadays everybody seem to want to get rid of it, doesn&amp;rsquo;t 
mean that it should be done, but let&amp;rsquo;s keep an eye out and an open mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another factor in Ruby&amp;rsquo;s excellent shape despite its age is certainly the new blood joining the community continuously. 
Ruby may not be as trendy as it was 10 years ago, but it&amp;rsquo;s still a common first language, for very good reasons, and having 
so many beginners in the community helps in a least two ways: it brings in new ideas, and forces us old-timers to stay 
welcoming and keep our craft accessible – or even inclusive. Yet, after realising how important the history of Ruby 
and its pioneers was for me, and seeing how many people were oblivious to it because they were not there then, I believe 
that we should do more to share these 30 years of history. &lt;a href=&quot;http://poignant.guide&quot;&gt;_why&amp;rsquo;s poignant guide&lt;/a&gt; deserves an update.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Euruko was also a great reminder that Ruby is greater than the Web, and is not limited to Rails. Yes, both these things 
have played a great role in Ruby&amp;rsquo;s popularity, and still do, and Rails in particular influences significantly Ruby, 
but this overlap should not limit Ruby&amp;rsquo;s horizon. One of the best talks this years was a demonstration of Ruby running 
on a computer so simple that it could only light up a LED. A very few talks even touched upon the Web, let alone Rails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, and unsurprisingly, I came back from Euruko with an exhilarating feeling of &lt;em&gt;belonging&lt;/em&gt;. Ruby was conceived 
for developer&amp;rsquo;s happiness, and developer – or, more broadly, people – are still at its core. This showed through Steve 
Backer&amp;rsquo;s personal talk, but also in Masafumi Okura sharing his delight of simply reading (abstruse) Ruby code, and 
obviously in Matz&amp;rsquo;s friendly, caring personality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Or maybe they were Gothic. Or Baroque. Or Neo-Classical. Vilnius&amp;rsquo; architecture is very rich, and I&amp;rsquo;m very ignorant.&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, as often, there was no parity in the speakers line-up, though.&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <id>https://2-45.pm/blog/blog/2023/09/07/brothers-up-in-arms.html</id>
      <title>Brothers (up) in Arms</title>
      <updated>2023-09-07T20:01:00+02:00</updated>

      <link rel="alternate" href="https://2-45.pm/blog/blog/2023/09/07/brothers-up-in-arms.html" />

      <published>2023-09-07T20:01:00+02:00</published>
      <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;For some reason, I&amp;rsquo;ve been binging on videos of Christopher Hitchens today and yesterday&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Now, the man did not always 
play fair, and was not above a cheap shot or two, but even if I don&amp;rsquo;t admire his oratory mastery as much as his fans 
in the YouTube comments, I&amp;rsquo;m in awe of his patience and his courage. The people he had to deal (or debate) with! Such 
ignorance, when not bigotry, under the guise of some righteous sense of being offended!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, these old debates and interviews were probably not a strong enough distraction from the current flame war in 
the Rails-adjacent community (the one that started with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://world.hey.com/dhh/turbo-8-is-dropping-typescript-70165c01&quot;&gt;removal of TypeScript from Turbo&lt;/a&gt;). 
This is irrational, but all the drama that is currently unfolding pains me. It makes me sad. And, just like with a 
train wreck, I cannot look away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I&amp;rsquo;ve spent a stupid amount of time reading threads on social media, discord servers, and pull requests, and all I get 
from this is a feeling of alienation. I see people reacting passionately, or at least intensely, and I cannot understand 
why. Putting aside the trolls would only like to sustain chaos for chaos&amp;rsquo;s sake (sometimes funnily, I must admit), there 
must be a reason why sane people, some of whom I have a good opinion of, brandish their pitchforks and use them to stroke 
the fires of online outrage – posting provocative manifestos, or encouraging the splitting of communities, for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find these reactions absurd, mean, and childish. But I cannot believe that so many developers are stupid, mean, or 
immature. Which means that these reactions must be logical and consistent &lt;em&gt;from their perspective&lt;/em&gt;. Which means that 
there is a gap, somewhere, between the way I (and others, I hope) see the world, and how these people see the world[^2]. 
And this pains me &lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also echoes the recent kerfuffle over Justin Searl&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.testdouble.com/posts/2023-07-12-the-looming-demise-of-the-10x-developer/&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; 
on generational divides between programmers, or this funny piece in the NY Times about 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2023/08/25/style/gen-x-generation-discourse.html&quot;&gt;the youngsters&amp;rsquo; scorn for Gen-Xers&lt;/a&gt;. So far, 
I&amp;rsquo;ve never had any issue connecting with people 5 years, 10 years, or 15 years younger than me; but now it seems like 
the people I&amp;rsquo;m sharing the world with just don&amp;rsquo;t see it the way I do, and vice versa. It worries me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will probably take a break from social media, and go re-read &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hachettebookgroup.com/titles/christopher-hitchens/god-is-not-great/9780446697965/?lens=twelve&quot;&gt;God Is Not Great&lt;/a&gt; 
instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I did not realise that his passing was 12 years ago already. Where have all these years gone?&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <id>https://2-45.pm/blog/blog/2023/08/28/what-i-ve-been-reading-lately-august-2023.html</id>
      <title>What I&#39;ve been reading lately (August 2023)</title>
      <updated>2023-08-28T08:34:00+02:00</updated>

      <link rel="alternate" href="https://2-45.pm/blog/blog/2023/08/28/what-i-ve-been-reading-lately-august-2023.html" />

      <published>2023-08-28T08:34:00+02:00</published>
      <content type="html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;une-histoire-du-jeu-vidéo-en-france-1960-1991-des-labos-and-chambres-dados-alexis-blanchet--guillaume-montagnon-2020&quot;&gt;Une histoire du jeu vidéo en France, 1960-1991: des labos and chambres d&amp;rsquo;ados (Alexis Blanchet &amp;amp; Guillaume Montagnon, 2020)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A book with a very long and exhaustive title (in English: &lt;em&gt;A history of video games in France, 1960-1991: from labs to 
teenagers&amp;rsquo; bedrooms&lt;/em&gt;), that fits perfectly with its content: a long and exhaustive study of, well, the way video games 
were made, distributed, and played from the early sixties to the start of the nineties. After 
&lt;a href=&quot;{% post_url 2023-05-25-what-i-ve-been-reading-lately %}&quot;&gt;Un feu dans le ciel nordique&lt;/a&gt;, this is another book that reads 
like a (friendly) PhD, with its analytical approach, its matter-of-fact tone devoid of any storytelling, and the very 
impressive amount of research that its built upon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if the first chapters (how video games were first disdained curiosities for researchers; how they eventually entered 
the realms of pinball-adjacent games for &lt;em&gt;cafés&lt;/em&gt; and bars) were a bit of a slog, albeit an interesting one, once 
we reached the 1970s and the home consoles, I got hooked; by the &amp;rsquo;80s, the time of the 8-bit home computers and my own 
youth, I could not put the book down. Learning the history behind all the companies whose names I used to read in 
magazines ads and game reviews – Infogrames, Ere Informatique, Ubi Soft… – was captivating. And, like with RPGs or 
start-ups, the synopsis is always the same. First, passionate enthusiasts tinker in their basement, then the money pours in, 
and finally consolidation kicks in, squeezing the fun to extract the dough. But as for the book, after a slow start, it 
was a great read!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-once-and-future-sex-going-medieval-on-womens-role-in-society-eleanor-janega-2023&quot;&gt;The Once And Future Sex: Going Medieval on Women&amp;rsquo;s Role in Society (Eleanor Janega, 2023)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that I heard about this one in an episode of Radio 4&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/p07mdbhg&quot;&gt;You&amp;rsquo;re Dead To Me&lt;/a&gt;. 
This would make sense, since like the podcast, this book is instructive, entertaining, friendly and witty. Unlike 
&lt;em&gt;Une Histoire du jeu vidéo…&lt;/em&gt;, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t go into too much details, giving you just enough to keep the narration lively 
and interesting. (Obviously, the author doesn&amp;rsquo;t need to assert her expertise, since it&amp;rsquo;s a given; this probably helps.) 
Even if the book&amp;rsquo;s structure is a bit obvious and repetitive – first the upcoming points are announced, then broadly 
introduced, then presented one by one, then summarised, and then we move on to the next topic – the author&amp;rsquo;s style 
and humour keep you hooked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what about the women&amp;rsquo;s role in medieval society? Unsurprisingly, it was major and yet underestimated and 
under-appreciated, and one of the author&amp;rsquo;s point is that it is still the case today – by which I mean that we fail to 
give medieval women justice, but also that we fail to give &lt;em&gt;modern&lt;/em&gt; women justice. The book&amp;rsquo;s conclusion articulates this 
point much better than me, but don&amp;rsquo;t expect the whole book to be a political manifesto: it is the work of an historian 
first, and a feminist second. Getting the whole picture of the medieval society&amp;rsquo;s view of women is a bit disheartening, 
because it&amp;rsquo;s both indisputably coherent and yet completely stupid – it makes perfect sense if your world view starts on 
fallacious premises. Which means that we still aren&amp;rsquo;t immune to such misguided ways (and more than once, I felt like I 
was reading something out of an incel manifesto.) All the more reason to enjoy this smart and witty book!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-black-dahlia-james-ellroy-1987&quot;&gt;The Black Dahlia (James Ellroy, 1987)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hadn&amp;rsquo;t read this book in 15 years, or maybe more, but had a good memory of it. Reading it now, I was a bit disappointed. 
From a stylistic point of view, it is a delight – Ellroy is as sharp and cold-blooded as Chandler, with a bit of extra 
crudeness to punch harder. But the story itself lacks a bit of cohesiveness – some of the things that are set up aren&amp;rsquo;t 
payed off, while some parts – especially towards the end – feel like fillers. The ending manages to tie everything up, 
but to do so resorts to one of the easiest tricks: it&amp;rsquo;s because they&amp;rsquo;re insane that the bad people did what they did (and 
a lot of characters turn out to be insane.) Still, I&amp;rsquo;m a sucker for stylish stories of hard-boiled detectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mountain-of-daggers-seth-skorkowsky-2015&quot;&gt;Mountain of Daggers (Seth Skorkowsky, 2015)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love &lt;a href=&quot;https://skorkowsky.com&quot;&gt;Seth Skorkowsky&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCQs8-UJ7IHsrzhQ-OQOYBmg&quot;&gt;videos&lt;/a&gt; 
on tabletop role-playing games. I indisputably deserves his &lt;a href=&quot;https://ennie-awards.com/2023-nominees/&quot;&gt;2023 ENNIE award&lt;/a&gt; 
for best podcast. And, since I&amp;rsquo;m always on the lookout for good fantasy novels, I was eager to read his work as a writer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I found the adventures of the Black Raven, good, but not great. The writing is perfectly fine – in fact, 
the action scenes grabbed me more than once – but I couldn&amp;rsquo;t care for the protagonist, nor the adventures themselves. 
The characters and the stories are a bit lacklustre, except for the very last story, with its disturbing, almost 
body-horror tone. I don&amp;rsquo;t know if the short stories in this book are adaptations of roleplaying sessions, but I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t 
be surprised if it was the case, because this is usually how it ends up: way less interesting to read than it must have 
been to play. Even the tales of the Black Company, which as far as I know are highly praised, eventually bored me. Still, 
Skorkowsky definitely knows how to write, so I&amp;rsquo;ll probably give his works another chance.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <id>https://2-45.pm/blog/blog/2023/09/07/tomorrow-people-tonight.html</id>
      <title>Tomorrow people tonight</title>
      <updated>2023-08-13T23:55:00+02:00</updated>

      <link rel="alternate" href="https://2-45.pm/blog/blog/2023/09/07/tomorrow-people-tonight.html" />

      <published>2023-08-13T23:55:00+02:00</published>
      <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;At the end of today, I was a few calories short of filling up my rings, and my dog didn&amp;rsquo;t feel like going out, so I went 
for a walk by myself, at night, listening to good music, as I used to do when I was a teenager.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, Billy Idol&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://music.apple.com/fr/album/cyberpunk/1442990930?l=en-GB&quot;&gt;Cyberpunk&lt;/a&gt; (1993) is probably the best 
record I know of. It is just incredible. The Paris suburbia I grew up in is not exactly The Sprawl, and yet, listening 
to this record while striding empty rurban streets used to put me in a perfect Gibsonian mood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, it didn&amp;rsquo;t work as well tonight. It could be because my bourgeois neighbourhood is impervious to
Blade-Runnerization, no matter how good your soundtrack is; or maybe, after a few decades, the weight of the years 
anchors your mind too deep for your imagination to carry it away that easily. Or maybe I was just distracted by my 
uncomfortable socks.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <id>https://2-45.pm/blog/blog/2023/08/04/2023-08-04-decaf-in-the-morning.html</id>
      <title>Decaf in the morning</title>
      <updated>2023-08-04T08:45:00+02:00</updated>

      <link rel="alternate" href="https://2-45.pm/blog/blog/2023/08/04/2023-08-04-decaf-in-the-morning.html" />

      <published>2023-08-04T08:45:00+02:00</published>
      <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The trickiest part of going back to blogging, a few months ago, was probably to decide on an editorial line. I&amp;rsquo;m still 
tinkering with it, but one thing is certain: I want this blog to be upbeat, and not over-sharing. In part because 
of the image I want to project, in part because, as my mother used to say, &lt;em&gt;“Small sorrows speak; great ones are silent”&lt;/em&gt;, 
but mostly because I believe that we should try to uplift the public discourse, and not add to the constant stream of 
negativity online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this may turn out to be a bit delicate as I write down my experience participating in the 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://railshackathon.com&quot;&gt;Rails Hackathon&lt;/a&gt; last week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the whole month, I had been waiting for this hackathon like a kid waits for Christmas. My previous and only experience 
participating in a Hackathon was in 2016, for the last Ruby Rampage, and it was great – we even ended up third! Needless 
to say, I was very confident for this one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enlisted 2 great devs I had worked with previously, and we came up with a great idea. We had a plan, we felt ready, 
I couldn&amp;rsquo;t wait for the hackathon to start – even if, unfortunately, the kick-off was at 2am here on the GMT +1 time zone. 
And yet, in the end we didn&amp;rsquo;t even submit our entry, because in spite of our efforts, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t ready. In fact, it was 
in the sorriest state a project can be, with all features started but none finished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My disappointment after throwing the towel was proportional to my excitement starting the project, and to be honest I 
felt depressed for a few days – to the point that I haven&amp;rsquo;t looked at the other entries, nor the winners, yet. And the 
more disturbing thing is that, no matter how I try to post-mortem this experience, I cannot escape the conclusion that
I&amp;rsquo;m responsible for this forfeiting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We faced difficulties managing the project (our goal was not as clear as we thought, the dispatching of the tasks was 
probably not optimal), and we lost a lot of time on the design, but these are normal hiccups in any project, and I 
don&amp;rsquo;t think that they are the root cause. And, obviously, none of my teammate is to blame for their effort or work – 
they both are really good developers and they did a great job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in retrospect, I believe that our team lacked &lt;em&gt;cohesion&lt;/em&gt;. It is a leadership failure, and I was the one acting 
as a leader. Which was doubly a mistake: first, I did a poor job of kind-of leading the team, but more importantly, I 
shouldn&amp;rsquo;t have taken this role in the first place! In my excitement, I failed to see that instead of nurturing everyone&amp;rsquo;s 
interest, involvement, and initiatives, I occupied all the space in our conversations, and certainly took the wind 
from my teammate&amp;rsquo;s sails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Considering my experience and the responsibilities I aspire to, this is very embarrassing. I&amp;rsquo;ll keep this lesson in mind 
and, hopefully, will do better next year!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <id>https://2-45.pm/blog/blog/2023/07/28/what-i-ve-been-reading-lately-july-2023.html</id>
      <title>What I&#39;ve been reading lately (July 2023)</title>
      <updated>2023-07-28T15:57:00+02:00</updated>

      <link rel="alternate" href="https://2-45.pm/blog/blog/2023/07/28/what-i-ve-been-reading-lately-july-2023.html" />

      <published>2023-07-28T15:57:00+02:00</published>
      <content type="html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;inside-the-skunkworks-machine-chris-dale-2022&quot;&gt;Inside the Skunkworks machine (Chris Dale, 2022)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;]Skunkworks](https://music.apple.com/fr/album/skunkworks-deluxe-edition/1146014243) is one of my favorite records, and 
has been for almost 30 years now. A textured rock album, it&amp;rsquo;s neither heavy metal (as fans of Bruce Dickinson would have 
hoped) nor grunge (as fans of Jack Endino would have guessed). It&amp;rsquo;s simply great, I love it, and it is a shame that what 
was supposed to be a lasting band turned out to be a short-lived project, quickly shelved so that Dickinson could go 
back to heavy metal (and subsequently Iron Maiden).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because they were so good, I kept track of the musicians behind Skunkworks for a while, especially Chris Dale, the 
bass player whose cool-looking instrument got me to cover my own bass with stickers. But I somehow missed a lot of 
things, including the self-publication of this book, by Dale, which covers everything about Skunkworks, the band, from 
the first auditions to the eventual disbanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In spite of its awful layout, Inside the Skunkworks machine is a great and riveting book – I couldn&amp;rsquo;t put it down and 
read it almost in one go, stoppig only for a few hours of sleep. It is much more captivating than Dickinson&amp;rsquo;s own 
autobiography, which turns to a slog of aeronautical anecdotes midway. Interestingly, Dickinson himself is 
rather absent from this book; not because he didn&amp;rsquo;t contribute (that&amp;rsquo;s only fair, it&amp;rsquo;s Dale&amp;rsquo;s book after all), but because 
he comes across as detached from the band&amp;rsquo;s life. Not taking part in the frequent jams between the 3 musicians, arriving 
late to the sound checks and leaving early after the shows – often to go fly planes… And yet, he was the one repeating 
than Skunkworks was a real band (including when I saw them in 1996 at the Elysée Montmartre), while neither the 
management nor Dale seemed to really believe it…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, Inside the Skunkworks machine is an exhaustive documentary on a great (albeit short-lived) musical project, 
and more importantly on a slice of the British rock scene of the mid-nineties and a bunch of passionate musicians who 
all, somehow, crossed the path of the ever-friendly Chris Dale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-last-of-us-que-reste-t-il-de-lhumanité-nicolas-deneschau-2021&quot;&gt;The Last of Us: que reste-t-il de l&amp;rsquo;humanité (Nicolas Deneschau, 2021)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My brother offered me this essay (in French) on the eponymous video games last Christmas; it tooks me 6 months to read it 
for 3 reasons: my backlog of books is shamefuly long, this one seemed a bit dry, and more importantly, I hadn&amp;rsquo;t recovered 
from the emotional Vietnam that &lt;em&gt;The Last of Us part II&lt;/em&gt; dragged me through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, it turns out that this book was not as emotionnaly taxing as I feared, if still a bit dry. Furthermore, I don&amp;rsquo;t 
really know what its point nor audience are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like the games alternate game and narrative sequences to unfold their stories, the book interlaces the retelling of said 
stories with either behind-the-scenes anecdotes or superficial gameplay analysis. This makes for an entertaining read, 
once you get used to its academic (and sometimes clumsly) voice, but not a very instructive one. Readers who have played 
the games probably don&amp;rsquo;t need their recap, while total newcomers could benefit from a more immersive narration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, this book barely more than a love letter from a fan who has studied the game and all the making-of 
documentaries. I may bring back some memories, and offer some trivia, but not much else.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <id>https://2-45.pm/blog/blog/a-dash-of-milk/2023/07/12/issue-5.html</id>
      <title>A dash of milk #5</title>
      <updated>2023-07-12T16:23:00+02:00</updated>

      <link rel="alternate" href="https://2-45.pm/blog/blog/a-dash-of-milk/2023/07/12/issue-5.html" />

      <published>2023-07-12T16:23:00+02:00</published>
      <content type="html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;minitest-focus&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/minitest/minitest-focus&quot;&gt;minitest-focus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the only things I miss from RSpec when using Minitest is the &lt;a href=&quot;http://rspec.info/features/3-12/rspec-core/filtering/inclusion-filters&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;:focus&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; 
metadata. You get used to filtering tests through command-line arguments, but it&amp;rsquo;s still a bit cumbersome, and lacks 
the elegance you can expect from such a Ruby-like tool as Minitest. So, of course there has to be a solution, and I 
was simply unaware of it. But, more importantly, &lt;code&gt;minitest-focus&lt;/code&gt; is a example of clean, smart-but-not-too-smart 
code. Just look at the way the “indirect approach” is implemented in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/minitest/minitest-focus/blob/02cbbc41519c04bf46b1bf14042e2a0ceddb7763/lib/minitest/focus.rb&quot;&gt;main file&lt;/a&gt;. 
It&amp;rsquo;s chef&amp;rsquo;s-kiss-emoji-level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-ai-help-button-is-very-good-but-it-links-to-a-feature-that-should-not-exist&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mdn/yari/issues/9230&quot;&gt;The AI help button is very good but it links to a feature that should not exist&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, it looks like &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/&quot;&gt;MDN Web Docs&lt;/a&gt; is trying out leveraging LLMs to enrich what is 
probably the best documentation site on the web. (And which will hopefully keep being so.) Well, color me surprised, 
but it doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem to work out so well. In any case, this issue is a really fun and interesting read – and, I think, a 
great way to raise and articulate concerns – and to circumvent overly zealous (or thickheaded) moderators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;garbage-collection-in-ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.peterzhu.ca/notes-on-ruby-gc/&quot;&gt;Garbage Collection in Ruby&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The internals of Ruby used to scare me – the only things I know about C, I learned by 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtube.com/playlist?list=PLPt8EM4KxGEVdozTFQ_taOdS6OFlNU7ki&quot;&gt;falling asleep to some German ASMR YouTuber&lt;/a&gt;. Not 
so much nowadays, and this kind of blog post is exactly the reason why. It&amp;rsquo;s well written, friendly, and makes complex 
topics seem simple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-simple-hash-table-in-c&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://theleo.zone/posts/hashmap-in-c/&quot;&gt;a simple hash table in C&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another nice article about complicated things, explained clearly. In a website with great “early web” vibes &amp;lt;3.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <id>https://2-45.pm/blog/blog/2023/07/10/brighton-ruby-2023.html</id>
      <title>Brighton Ruby 2023</title>
      <updated>2023-07-10T11:31:00+02:00</updated>

      <link rel="alternate" href="https://2-45.pm/blog/blog/2023/07/10/brighton-ruby-2023.html" />

      <published>2023-07-10T11:31:00+02:00</published>
      <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last week was my first time attending &lt;a href=&quot;https://brightonruby.com&quot;&gt;Brighton Ruby&lt;/a&gt;. It was great. I&amp;rsquo;ve missed conferences 
in general, and &lt;em&gt;Ruby&lt;/em&gt; conferences in particular, and Brighton Ruby was everything I was longing for: an energising mix 
of technical considerations and humanist values, shared by smart and colourful people. Nerdy and yet friendly, like a 
grown-up version of the role-playing games clubs of my youth. Beware: this post will be a test of how many synonyms I 
know for “great”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-venue-and-the-organisation&quot;&gt;The venue and the organisation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conference took place at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://brightondome.org&quot;&gt;Brighton Dome&lt;/a&gt;, which is more impressive than I was expecting. 
The main hall is lovely, its seats confortable enough, and the stage, lighting and audio were perfect. I came in early, 
and the welcome process was very smooth – no queue nor waiting of any kind. However, the small hall where everyone could 
gather before and between the actual talks was a bit too small for the attendance, and quickly got crowded and 
very noisy. That would be my only complain as far as the organisation goes: by all other accounts, everything was 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thesaurus.com/browse/great&quot;&gt;excellent&lt;/a&gt;, from the coffee and pastries to Andy&amp;rsquo;s wholehearted MCing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-talks&quot;&gt;The talks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I bought my ticket without knowing anything of the conference&amp;rsquo;s program, and only discovered it once within the venue. 
Reading it got me excited. Eileen Uchitelle! Librarians! Contrarian-sounding topics! The program promised and lot – and 
delivered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The highlights, for me, were probably &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/threedaymonk/back-in-my-day&quot;&gt;Paul Battley&amp;rsquo;s lightning talk about Ruby through the past 20 years&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://nadiaodunayo.com&quot;&gt;Nadia Odunayo&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s talk on a “vanished variable”, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.joehartcomedian.com&quot;&gt;Joe Hart&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s 
comedy-and-live-debugging bit. But, honestly, all the talks – even the lightning ones – were &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thesaurus.com/browse/great&quot;&gt;fantastic&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from my personal favorites, three of the talks stood out, I think. First, even though I had already seen it, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MbqJzACF-54&quot;&gt;Eileen&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; was both insightful and powerful – I highly recommend watching 
it. Second, &lt;a href=&quot;https://timriley.info&quot;&gt;Tim Riley&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s, for its &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thesaurus.com/browse/great&quot;&gt;awesome&lt;/a&gt; performance 
– even if I&amp;rsquo;m now 100% percent convinced that Hanami is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; for me (this project&amp;rsquo;s priorities are definitely not mine, 
but YMMV and it&amp;rsquo;s nice to have something for everyone in the Ruby ecosystem). Third, &lt;a href=&quot;https://schwad.github.io&quot;&gt;Schwad&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s 
talk on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/scarpe-team/scarpe&quot;&gt;Scarpe&lt;/a&gt;, which was an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thesaurus.com/browse/great&quot;&gt;admirable&lt;/a&gt; 
hommage to _why (and I was glad to see how many people still know about him, even among the new generation of rubyists).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I must underscore the model of diversity that this line-up was. A broad mix of ages, genders, backgrounds, 
ethnicities and topics was assembled, which was certainly not by accident – even if I dare hope that achieving this was 
easier in 2023 than it would have been 10 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-people&quot;&gt;The people&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talks are always nice, but the essence of a conference is the attendance, and the opportunity to meet new people. Now, 
like many in this line of work, I&amp;rsquo;m more on the shy and solitary side of the social spectrum. Even though I really, really 
enjoy having small talk or deep conversations with friendly strangers, it takes me some time and energy (possibly in the 
form of drinks) to switch to extrovert mode. Which is fine, especially in the Ruby community where everyone MINASWANs. 
Besides, I already knew a couple of attendants, including a true social hub, which helped quite a bit (thank you 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://ruby.social/@benoit&quot;&gt;Benoît&lt;/a&gt;!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, due to the people density and loudness in the rest area, I didn&amp;rsquo;t spend that much time socialising during the breaks, 
unfortunately. But I enjoyed good drinks and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thesaurus.com/browse/great&quot;&gt;wonderful&lt;/a&gt; company after the 
conference, when a bunch of us gathered in local pubs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, here&amp;rsquo;s the thing. Fifteen years ago, I managed to convince my then boss to switch our stack to Ruby by promoting 
the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thesaurus.com/browse/great&quot;&gt;exceptionality&lt;/a&gt; of the people in this community – yes, rubyists were hard 
to find, but they were a humble elite among a sea of unfortunate code monkeys. Well, I may be biased here, but even after 
all this time, a couple of years of fame (that&amp;rsquo;s 15 minutes in VC time) and hordes of bootcamp graduates, my assessment 
still stands. The people I talked to at Brighton Ruby were all &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thesaurus.com/browse/great&quot;&gt;terrific&lt;/a&gt;, and 
I&amp;rsquo;m pretty sure that my sample was 100% representative of the attendance, and more broadly of the Ruby community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;generations&quot;&gt;Generations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This general &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thesaurus.com/browse/great&quot;&gt;marvellousness&lt;/a&gt; is all the better considering my personal worries 
about the Balkanising of our societies, including code communities. It&amp;rsquo;s one of the things that keep me up at night – 
expect a blog post on of these days. I see fracture lines creeping up everywhere, splitting every group into smaller and 
smaller polarised (if not outright hostile!) tribes, and the Ruby community, and even more so the Rails community, are 
not spared. And maybe it&amp;rsquo;s just me because I&amp;rsquo;m on my way to my fifties, but I tend to see one of these fractures lines 
in the generational gaps in our craft&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; especially after two years recruiting outside of my usual 
tech pool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, it turns out that there were &lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;/em&gt; of youngsters[^2] in the attendance, and they impressed me 
&lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;/em&gt;. Enthusiastic, (very) knowledgeable, smart… Exactly the kind of people I like to believe that my comrades and I 
were back in the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, I came out of Brighton Ruby feeling both happy, reassured, and also a bit like shit. That&amp;rsquo;s because so many people 
were &lt;em&gt;so fucking impressive&lt;/em&gt;. Be they 15 years younger than me and already as experienced as I feel[^3], or people my age 
with five times my list of achievements, I felt surrounded by raw talent across two or three generations of developers. 
Which is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thesaurus.com/browse/great&quot;&gt;tremendous&lt;/a&gt; thing for the community (and the future or programming), 
but made me feel small. At the same time, it&amp;rsquo;s never too late catch up!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brighton Ruby was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thesaurus.com/browse/great&quot;&gt;super-duper&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ll be back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Edit:&lt;/strong&gt; as &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.testdouble.com/posts/2023-07-12-the-looming-demise-of-the-10x-developer/&quot;&gt;a viral blog post by Justin Searls&lt;/a&gt; 
showed, it turns out that it isn&amp;rsquo;t just me at all. I always feel better when someone smarter than me thinks as I do.
[^2]: I&amp;rsquo;m 46, I&amp;rsquo;m allowed to use this word. Now get off my lawn.
[^3]: Time to quote &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pYGiDX9Luc8&quot;&gt;The Hellacopters&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;em&gt;And I&amp;rsquo;m older but sure ain&amp;rsquo;t as wise as I pretend to, it&amp;rsquo;s mostly a lie.&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <id>https://2-45.pm/blog/blog/a-dash-of-milk/2023/06/26/issue-4.html</id>
      <title>A dash of milk #4</title>
      <updated>2023-06-26T20:50:00+02:00</updated>

      <link rel="alternate" href="https://2-45.pm/blog/blog/a-dash-of-milk/2023/06/26/issue-4.html" />

      <published>2023-06-26T20:50:00+02:00</published>
      <content type="html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;attenborough-lore&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/@AttenboroughLore/about&quot;&gt;Attenborough Lore&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;A foray into the Warhammer 40,000 lore, as narrated by an AI of the venerable Sir David Attenborough.&amp;rdquo; I&amp;rsquo;ve 
been binging on these videos recently – the richness and horror of the 40K lore pairs really well, in an ironic way, with 
Sir Attenborough&amp;rsquo;s simulated elocution. The results are really impressive – finally a good use of deep fake tech!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;intel-one-mono&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/intel/intel-one-mono&quot;&gt;Intel One Mono&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a sucker for fonts, especially so-called progamming fronts. This one looked really good… on the screenshots. I installed it 
and immediately went back to my dear &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fontspace.com/monofur-font-f39937&quot;&gt;Monofur&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;webxr&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://immersiveweb.dev&quot;&gt;WebXR&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m really excited by visionOS and the idea of “spatial computing”. I&amp;rsquo;m usually suspicious of attempts to use web tech to 
build desktop-like apps, but this may be an easy way in this new landscape. I&amp;rsquo;m willing go give it a try. (But I&amp;rsquo;m also downloading 
XCode and dusting off my Swift reference book as I&amp;rsquo;m typing this…)&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </entry>
  
</feed>
  </div>
</article>
  </main>
  <footer>
    <p class="h-card">
      <a href="/work-with-me.html#even-more-about-me">
        <span class="p-given-name">Ronan</span> <span class="p-family-name">Limon Duparcmeur</span>
      </a>
    </p>
    
    <ul class="footer-links">
      <li>
        <a href="https:/ruby.social/@r3trofitted">
          <svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="16" height="16" fill="currentColor" class="bi bi-mastodon" viewBox="0 0 16 16">
            <path d="M11.19 12.195c2.016-.24 3.77-1.475 3.99-2.603.348-1.778.32-4.339.32-4.339 0-3.47-2.286-4.488-2.286-4.488C12.062.238 10.083.017 8.027 0h-.05C5.92.017 3.942.238 2.79.765c0 0-2.285 1.017-2.285 4.488l-.002.662c-.004.64-.007 1.35.011 2.091.083 3.394.626 6.74 3.78 7.57 1.454.383 2.703.463 3.709.408 1.823-.1 2.847-.647 2.847-.647l-.06-1.317s-1.303.41-2.767.36c-1.45-.05-2.98-.156-3.215-1.928a3.614 3.614 0 0 1-.033-.496s1.424.346 3.228.428c1.103.05 2.137-.064 3.188-.189zm1.613-2.47H11.13v-4.08c0-.859-.364-1.295-1.091-1.295-.804 0-1.207.517-1.207 1.541v2.233H7.168V5.89c0-1.024-.403-1.541-1.207-1.541-.727 0-1.091.436-1.091 1.296v4.079H3.197V5.522c0-.859.22-1.541.66-2.046.456-.505 1.052-.764 1.793-.764.856 0 1.504.328 1.933.983L8 4.39l.417-.695c.429-.655 1.077-.983 1.934-.983.74 0 1.336.259 1.791.764.442.505.661 1.187.661 2.046v4.203z"/>
          </svg>
        </a>
      </li>
      <li>
        <a href="https://github.com/r3trofitted">
          <svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="16" height="16" fill="currentColor" class="bi bi-github" viewBox="0 0 16 16">
            <path d="M8 0C3.58 0 0 3.58 0 8c0 3.54 2.29 6.53 5.47 7.59.4.07.55-.17.55-.38 0-.19-.01-.82-.01-1.49-2.01.37-2.53-.49-2.69-.94-.09-.23-.48-.94-.82-1.13-.28-.15-.68-.52-.01-.53.63-.01 1.08.58 1.23.82.72 1.21 1.87.87 2.33.66.07-.52.28-.87.51-1.07-1.78-.2-3.64-.89-3.64-3.95 0-.87.31-1.59.82-2.15-.08-.2-.36-1.02.08-2.12 0 0 .67-.21 2.2.82.64-.18 1.32-.27 2-.27.68 0 1.36.09 2 .27 1.53-1.04 2.2-.82 2.2-.82.44 1.1.16 1.92.08 2.12.51.56.82 1.27.82 2.15 0 3.07-1.87 3.75-3.65 3.95.29.25.54.73.54 1.48 0 1.07-.01 1.93-.01 2.2 0 .21.15.46.55.38A8.012 8.012 0 0 0 16 8c0-4.42-3.58-8-8-8z" />
          </svg>
        </a>
      </li>
      <li>
        <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/r3trofitted">
          <svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="16" height="16" fill="currentColor" class="bi bi-linkedin" viewBox="0 0 16 16">
            <path d="M0 1.146C0 .513.526 0 1.175 0h13.65C15.474 0 16 .513 16 1.146v13.708c0 .633-.526 1.146-1.175 1.146H1.175C.526 16 0 15.487 0 14.854V1.146zm4.943 12.248V6.169H2.542v7.225h2.401zm-1.2-8.212c.837 0 1.358-.554 1.358-1.248-.015-.709-.52-1.248-1.342-1.248-.822 0-1.359.54-1.359 1.248 0 .694.521 1.248 1.327 1.248h.016zm4.908 8.212V9.359c0-.216.016-.432.08-.586.173-.431.568-.878 1.232-.878.869 0 1.216.662 1.216 1.634v3.865h2.401V9.25c0-2.22-1.184-3.252-2.764-3.252-1.274 0-1.845.7-2.165 1.193v.025h-.016a5.54 5.54 0 0 1 .016-.025V6.169h-2.4c.03.678 0 7.225 0 7.225h2.4z" />
          </svg>
        </a>
      </li>
      <li>
        <a href="/feed.xml">
          <svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="16" height="16" fill="currentColor" class="bi bi-rss-fill" viewBox="0 0 16 16">
            <path d="M2 0a2 2 0 0 0-2 2v12a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h12a2 2 0 0 0 2-2V2a2 2 0 0 0-2-2H2zm1.5 2.5c5.523 0 10 4.477 10 10a1 1 0 1 1-2 0 8 8 0 0 0-8-8 1 1 0 0 1 0-2zm0 4a6 6 0 0 1 6 6 1 1 0 1 1-2 0 4 4 0 0 0-4-4 1 1 0 0 1 0-2zm.5 7a1.5 1.5 0 1 1 0-3 1.5 1.5 0 0 1 0 3z" />
          </svg>
        </a>
      </li>
    </ul>
    <!-- SVG gradient for the icons -->
<svg aria-hidden="true" focusable="false" style="width:0;height:0;position:absolute;">
  <defs>
    <linearGradient x1="0.085" y1="0.085" x2="0.915" y2="0.915" id="rss-gradient">
      <stop offset="0.0" stop-color="#E3702D" />
      <stop offset="0.1071" stop-color="#EA7D31" />
      <stop offset="0.3503" stop-color="#F69537" />
      <stop offset="0.5" stop-color="#FB9E3A" />
      <stop offset="0.7016" stop-color="#EA7C31" />
      <stop offset="0.8866" stop-color="#DE642B" />
      <stop offset="1.0" stop-color="#D95B29" />
    </linearGradient>
    <linearGradient x1="0.0" y1="0" x2="0.0" y2="1.0" id="mastodon-gradient">
      <stop stop-color="#6364FF"/>
      <stop offset="1" stop-color="#563ACC"/>
    </linearGradient>
  </defs>
</svg>
  </footer>
</body>
</html>
